CHILDREN OF IRENA SENDLER
片名：勇敢的护士(伊雷娜 森德勒的孩子们)
In the memory of all the known and unknown who are, "Righteous Among the Nations".
谨以本片纪念那些知名的和不知名的“国际义人”
Yes?
喂？
Yes.
嗯
Yes, I will come right away.
好的，我马上过来
I will walk, so twenty minutes.
走过来，二十分钟就到
Please, stay calm.
保持冷静
Irenka?
伊雷卡（伊雷娜的昵称）？
It's all right, Mama. Go back to sleep.
没事儿，妈妈，回去睡觉吧
- Thank God, you are here. - Where is she?
- 感谢上帝！你来了 - 她在哪里？
In the cupboard.
在碗橱里
Tonight, when Krzysztof came home the way our neighbours looked at him
今晚，克里日托夫回家的时候邻居奇怪地盯着他
we were betrayed. I just know. I'm sorry, Irena.
我想我们暴露了，对不起，伊雷娜
If the Germans find us hiding a Jew, they will shoot us.
如果德国人发现我们藏着一个犹太人，他们会杀了我们的
Hello, Anna, it's Irena.
你好，安娜，是伊雷娜
You do not need to be afraid. And tonight...
不要害怕
you will stay with me.
今晚你跟我住
How many mothers do you have?
你有几个妈妈？
I just have one.
只有一个
Already, I had three.
我有三个
Shh.
嘘...
Why do they not like me?
为什么她们都不喜欢我？
Who does not like you?
谁不喜欢你？
My mothers.
我的三个妈妈
Your mothers love you. And I love you.
她们都爱你，我也爱你
And I will always love you.
而且我会永远爱你
Go to sleep.
好了，睡觉吧
- We have to go now. - Here.
- 我们要走了 - 给你
It is safe to take her out in broad daylight?
大白天带她出去安全吗？
She looks like one of us. Are you worried?
她看起来和我们一样，你还担心吗？
Not one bit.
一点也不担心
Mama, hmm?
妈妈？
- Ahh, good. - Eva will love it.
- 啊，很好。 - 伊娃会喜欢的
It's perfect.
这样看起来棒极了
Mama! Take your medicine.
妈妈！吃药
Mama, please.
来
You are so funny. You're a wonderful girl.
你真有趣，好姑娘
The second doll with the long locks was called Bella.
我第二个洋娃娃叫贝拉，有长长的头发
Come in Anna!
进来，安娜
Anna, this is Miss Jadwiga.
安娜，这是雅德维加小姐.
Hello, sweetie. Come in.
你好，亲爱的 进来吧
Thank you. Come in.
谢谢，进来
Anna, you can play with Miss Jadwiga's children while
安娜，去和雅德维加小姐的孩子们玩
I find you a lovely place to live. You're a good girl.
我给你找一个住的地方 好姑娘
- Take care of her. - Hello, sweetie.
- 好好照顾她 - 你好，亲爱的
She has passed outside the ghetto all this time. There must be
她这段时间都在隔离区外面
- a Polish family who can take her. - Not any we know personally.
- 必须找个波兰家庭来照顾她 - 就我所知没人愿意的
I'll ask father Godlewski he will know some we can trust.
我要去找戈德莱夫斯基神父 他知道一些我们可以信任的家庭
- You're going to the Ghetto? - Yes. I will see you later.
- 你要去隔离区？ - 是的，回头见
Get out of here.
滚开
Irena Sendler, you work?
伊雷娜 森德勒，你的工作？
Department of Social Services.
社会服务部
I see that, my question is about today, why are you here?
我知道，我的意思是你今天到这里做什么？
Inspection of the refugee centers. Prevent the spread of typhus.
检查难民中心（隔离区） 预防伤寒传播
You Poles must solve this problem, it's a disgrace.
你们波兰人必须解决这个问题，这是个不光彩的事情
Go in.
进去吧
Next please, documents.
下一个，证件
Only bread today, take it. Go.
今天只有这些面包了，拿着 走吧
You're not hungry?
你不饿吗？
Please, please buy it from me.
买点，买点什么吧
Father Godlewski. Good morning.
戈德莱夫斯基神父，早上好
Ah, Irena.
啊，伊雷娜
What do you hear?
你听说什么了吗？
In the last two weeks, they have filled train cars of Jews in Luxemburg and
在过去的两周里，他们用火车把
Vienna, deported them all to the ghetto in Lodz - and here,
卢森堡和维也纳的犹太人驱逐到罗兹和这里的隔离区
every day they bring more.
每天都运来越来越多的人
You know we are doing all we can to help Jews survive outside the ghetto.
我们正在尽一切努力去帮助隔离区外幸存下来的犹太人
- Yes, I know, very well. - And today I have a little girl
- 是的，我知道，很好 - 我现在就有一个犹太女孩需要帮助
- and no Polish family to hide her. - It's not easy for Poles either.
- 没有波兰家庭肯收留她 - 波兰家庭也不容易
- Perhaps in your congregation? - Irena, please...
- 也许你能动员一个（波兰家庭来收留她） - 伊雷娜...
...of all people you know the risk for a Polish family.
...所有人都知道这是非常危险的
Even so, is it not possible there are some or even many Poles who want
尽管这样，有没有可能
Yes, yes, yes. It is possible.
是的是的，有这个可能（我试着找找吧）
Eva.
伊娃
Irena.
伊雷娜
Come, come.
进来，进来
- Good morning, Hannah. - Oh, Irenka.
- 早上好，汉娜 - 噢，伊雷娜
Always such a faithful friend.
多么可靠的朋友啊
God bless you.
上帝保佑你
Rabbi Rozenfeld.
罗兹菲尔德法师
Dear Irena, how are you this fine day?
亲爱的伊雷娜，这几天过得怎么样？
Is this work for a Rabbi?
这是法师该做的？
We all must live with dignity, especially in days of hatred.
我们必须活得有尊严， 特别是在充满仇恨的年代里
Miss Irena! Miss Irena!
伊雷娜！伊雷娜！
Karolyna! Or should I say, the famous Miss Nijinska, Prima ballerina?
卡罗玲娜！或者我该称呼你为著名的 娜金斯卡小姐，芭蕾舞团首席女演员？
Do you know what I learned to do! Do you want to see?
你知道我学了什么吗！ 你想看看吗？
Of course, you must show me!
当然，让我看看！
Brava!
哇！
- How is your mother? - Well enough, if she behaves.
- 你妈妈怎么样？ - 很好
- And your Jacob? - Last week he came back into
- 那么你的雅各布呢？ - 上个星期他回隔离区来看女儿
Maybe yes, a little.
是的，也许
I brought a few things.
我带来了些东西
Let me, let me!
让我看看！让我看看！
And this.
还有这些
Irena, what do we have here?
伊雷娜，这里面是什么？
You made this?
你做的？
Can you imagine me putting two stitches together?
我有这么好的针线活吗？
- Then your mother. - She misses you.
- 你妈妈做的？ - 是，她很想你
So do I.
我也是
My dearest friends in the whole world.
你是我最好的朋友
Please thank her.
替我谢谢你妈妈
Eva, I need to talk with you.
伊娃，我要和你谈谈
Over the last few weeks, they have deported freight cars
过去的几个星期里，
of Jews from Austria to the ghetto in Lodz.
他们整车整车的把澳大利亚的犹太人送到罗兹的隔离区
We heard last night. The Jewish Council says they will send to workcamps.
我们是昨晚听说的，犹太委员会 说他们很快就会被送到劳工营去
Eva, your Jewish Council was appointed by Germans. How many years have we listened to
伊娃，犹太委员会已经被德国人控制了
their terrible propaganda? What they say about Jews, what they say
这么长时间以来他们是怎样宣传的？ 他们是怎么说犹太人的，他们怎么说来着
- they have in mind... - It's just talk, rumor.
- 他们只想着... - 这只是流言，谣传
Who can believe it? These are cultured people. Anyway, we're
谁会相信这些？他们都是很不错的人
almost five hundred thousand in this Ghetto. What could they do?
尽管这样，隔离区里有五十万人，他们能做些什么呢？
Yes, yes... I know.
是的，是的... 我知道
It's so confusing.
这些都是乱七八糟的
One day somebody says something is true, another says it's not.
有些人说是这样，又有些人说是那样
Every day I wake up, my body is cold.
每天早上醒来，我都感觉又冷又怕
We have to get you all out of here.
我们必须把你们弄出去
They would never leave. I could never leave them.
他们不会走的 我也绝不离开他们
I can find Polish families willing to hide you.
我能找几个波兰朋友把你藏起来
Most people believe it's better to stay all together, inside the wall.
大部分人认为最好呆在一起，在隔离区里
I want you safe...
我要你们安全...
...all of you. - Irena, what is safe?
...你们所有人 - 伊雷娜，什么是安全？
Where?
在哪里？
Good morning, Miss Irena.
早上好，伊雷娜小姐
Good morning, Doctor Majkowski, have you had a chance to consider my...
早上好，麦考斯基医生 你有没有考虑...
Yes, I have selected your friend, Maria Debinska to join your department.
是的，我选择了你的好友玛丽亚 迪宾斯卡 她会到你的部门
Thank you, doctor.
谢谢，医生
- Good morning. - Good morning, Miss Irena.
- 早上好 - 早上好，伊雷娜小姐
Maria, welcome to our little department, thank you.
玛丽亚，欢迎到我的部门，谢谢
My thanks to you.
也谢谢你
- Good morning, Miss Irena. - You missed an exciting meeting.
- 早上好，伊雷娜小姐 - 你错过了一个令人激动的会议
Issued today, the new ration card.
今天的焦点，新的食物配给
2613 calories a day for Germans, 699 calories for Poles,
德国人每天2613卡路里， 波兰人699卡路里
300 calories for residents of the ghetto.
隔离区里的300卡路里
So we will have starvation along with a Typhus epidemic.
那么我们会有饥饿还有伤寒（要处理）
And winter almost here.
还有冬天就快到了
We'll need to bring in food, clothing, medicine - Maria,
我们要带去食物、衣服、药品
talk to Doctor Majkowski, see how much Typhus vaccine you can get.
玛丽亚，问问麦考斯基医生能给你多少伤寒疫苗
Since The Occupation Jadwiga has done a brilliant job of trying
虽然雅德维加在平衡预算方面一直做得很出色
But...
但是...
But, if we continue to spread our services over every district in Warsaw,
但是，如果我们继续在华沙的各个区展开我们的服务
we will not be helping anyone.
那我们谁也救不了
From now on we must focus our full attention on the ghetto.
从现在开始，我们必须把精力集中到隔离区里
Excuse me, Miss Irena. The Jewish Quarter is not our problem.
抱歉，打断一下，伊雷娜小姐 犹太人区域与我们无关
Why not?
为什么？
The Germans put them there to protect us.
德国人把他们放在那里是为了保护我们
Protect us from what?
保护我们什么？
Maria, you are a nurse, you know very well.
玛丽亚，你是个护士， 你知道得很清楚
What do I know, tell me?
我知道什么，告诉我？
They have lice, spread disease and...
他们长虱子，传播疾病，还有...
You know what I'm talking about.
你知道我在说什么
Danuta, how can half a million cramped people stay in good health.
达努塔，五十万人挤在那么个地方怎么会不生病呢？
One reason, another reason what does it matter.
好吧，这个原因，那个原因，这又有什么关系
All I know is I am not going to bring Typhus home to my family.
我所知道的是我不想把伤寒带回家，传染给我的家人
Whatever it is you're thinking,
不管你怎么想
I am sorry - I can't be part of it.
对不起 - 我不能再干下去了
Anyone else who does not agree with this direction,
还有谁不同意这个决定
I will arrange a department transfer.
我可以调她到其他部门
Stefania, you have only been with us two months.
斯特凡尼亚，你才来了两个月
I have not yet been inside the walls, but I know I must do it.
我还没有去过隔离区，但我想我必须进去看看
Stefania. We are at war.
斯特凡尼亚，我们是在战斗
You are a soldier now. A soldier must be tough or she cannot fight.
你现在是一个士兵，士兵必须坚强，否则她就无法战斗
Oh! Hold her. Hold her still, good, good.
按住她。 让她别动，好，好
- Why do you bother? - Because we want your child to survive.
- 你为什么要这样对她？ - 因为我们想要你的孩子活下来
If you want her to live, please, take her from me, get her out of here.
如果你想要她活下来， 请把她带走，带她离开这里
I'm begging you, take her outside the wall.
我在求你，带她离开隔离区
- I'm sorry. - It's not possible.
- 对不起 - 这不可能
Next!
下一位！
Please, Mama, go back to bed.
求求你，妈妈，去睡觉吧
I am fine. Do not worry.
我很好，不用担心
What is it?
怎么了？
Tell me.
告诉我
Irena?
伊雷卡？
Irenka, tell me what.
伊雷卡，告诉我怎么了？
Today, I understood something.
今天，我明白了一些事情
Something about what?
什么事情
I thought I was doing all I could
我原以为我做了一切我能做的
but the truth is I am doing nothing.
但事实是我什么也没做
Nothing?
什么也没做？
Is it my imagination or was there a little Jewish child
是我的幻觉还是昨晚有一个犹太孩子睡在你的床上
One child is not enough!
一个孩子远远不够！
Oh Irena, you are so like your father.
噢，伊雷卡，你太像你的父亲了
Little Anna has always lived outside the Ghetto.
小安娜一直都在隔离区外
Inside the wall there are thousands of children who could be rescued.
在隔离区里有数千个孩子等着人救
Take them out?
带他们出来？
Is that what you're thinking?
这就是你在想的？
Past the Gestapo?
在盖世太保的眼皮下？
German soldiers, Jewish police?
还有德国兵，犹太警察
How is that possible?
这怎么可能？
You are a social worker,
伊雷卡，你是个社会工作者
a good social worker
一个出色的社会工作者
with the biggest heart I know but to risk everything for something you know
有着在我看来最火热的激情
I remember what father used to say.
我还记得父亲过去常说
You see a man drowning, you must try to save him,
你看见一个人快要淹死了，你必须设法救他
even if you can't swim.
即使你不会游泳
For you?
你要什么？
Two loaves, please.
两个面包
- You are a Jew. - No, I'm not.
- 你是犹太人 - 不，我不是
One of those filthy little smugglers from the ghetto.
一个隔离区逃出来的肮脏的小走私贩
No, I'm Polish.
不，我是波兰人
Let's see you make the sign of the cross!
划个十字圣号给我看看！ (基督教徒祈祷时划十字，犹太人不信基督教)
Let's go!
跟我走！
With this red hair, you do not think you look Jewish?
长着红色头发，你以为你看起来还不像犹太人吗？
- And get yourself a cap. - Yes, miss.
- 找个帽子戴上 - 是，小姐
If you want to survive outside the Ghetto you must lie with
如果你想在隔离区外不被人出来
more conviction. And learn how to cross yourself. Like this. Now, you.
你必须装的更像一点，学会怎样划十字 像这样，现在做给我看
Again. Quickly!
再来，做快一点
Very good. Get out of here.
很好，走吧
Wait!
等等！
Who is it?
谁在那儿？
Hide! They're coming here. Shh.
藏好！ 他们过来了，嘘...
I'm afraid.
我好怕
I want to help children inside, the, ghetto.
我想帮助隔离区里的孩子
It is very dangerous - too dangerous.
那很危险 - 太危险了
Yes, probably, but what would it take?
是的，也许，那样做需要些什么？
Well, I suppose an organized network of people you trust, enough money
呃，我想需要...组织可以信任的人，
for each child's room and board.
还有孩子们食宿的足够的钱
And if you agree, more Polish families willing to hide a Jewish child.
如果你认同，更多的波兰家庭会愿意隐藏犹太孩子
- I will try to find some. - What about identity cards?
- 我会试着找一些的 - 身份证怎么办？
That shouldn't be hard, if I destroy some of the parish death certificates,
这应该不难，我可以销毁一些教区的死亡证明
issue new baptismal certificates.
签发新的受洗证
That is all the proof Germans need for an identity card.
做身份证只需要受洗证
The only thing is, how to get them out?
剩下的就是， 怎么把他们弄出来
There is someone you must talk to... a young man who smuggles
你必须见一个人...
potatoes from the Aryan side, he works in Korczak's orphanage.
一个从隔离区外偷运土豆的年轻人， 他在考瑞查克的孤儿院工作
Ask him to introduce you to Stefan Zgrzembski.
让他介绍你认识斯忒芬 斯格拉博斯基
- Zgrzembski? - Yes, that's him.
- 斯格拉博斯基？ - 是的
Guten morgen, Father.
(德语)早上好，神父
Doctor Korczak, how many children live inside the ghetto?
考瑞查克医生，在隔离区里有多少孩子？
Including all the ones who live in the streets? There must be at least
包括那些无家可归的？
eighty thousand, half under the age of ten. Be brave now.
至少有八千个，一半是十岁以下的 勇敢点
Have you ever tried to get any out?
你有没有想过把他们送出去？
Out to where?
去哪里？
Not so many Poles want to hide a Jewish child.
没有那么多波兰人想藏犹太孩子的
And how many Jews would let their children live with Gentiles?
又有多少犹太人想让他们的孩子和异教徒一起生活？
What about orphans, these ones?
那么孤儿呢，这些孤儿？
Even if you found a way, most of mine could not survive outside the wall.
即使你想出了办法，我的大部分孩子在外面会活不下去的
- Why not? - She only speaks Yiddish. Is that not right?
- 为什么？ - 她只会说依地语(犹太人使用的国际语)，这是个问题吧？
They all speak excellent Yiddish. Polish, that's another matter.
他们说一口流利的依地语 波兰语，他们一点都不懂
And they are all beautiful
还有，他们虽然都很漂亮
but most are not passable as Aryan.
但大部分都不像雅利安人
Irena?
伊雷娜？
Oh, Stefan.
噢，斯忒芬
It's been a long time.
好久不见了
Irena is here to see you.
伊雷娜是来找你的
You attended my classes together.
你们一起上过我的课
Yes, a long time ago.
是的，很久以前了
Let me deal with these
让我来处理
horrible little savages!
小淘气们！哈哈...
I have found something here with Doctor Korczak and the children.
在这里，和考瑞查克医生还有孩子们在一起让我感到很有意义
I am glad. But you still smuggle potatoes.
我很高兴 但是你还在偷运土豆
Irena Sendler, always straight to the point.
伊雷娜护士，你总是开门见山
Tell me how.
告诉我你是怎么做的
I know a few safe ways to get out, the courthouse has two ways out,
我知道一些通向外面的安全的路， 法院有一条
one from the ghetto side and one from the Aryan side.
一端通向隔离区，另一端通向外面
That's in the ghetto, from the Aryan side it's by Ogrodowa street.
隔离区那一端就在花园街上
I... I know a man with the key.
我... 我认识看门的人
- The other ways? - I can show you.
- 其他的路呢？ - 我带你去看
The main sewer line goes all the way down to the central junction under Gdanski station.
主要的污水管道都通向但斯克站下的污水枢纽中心
- And from there? - Anywhere you want.
- 可以通向哪里？ - 你想去的任何地方
One line goes under Okopowa Street,
有一条管道通向奥克珀瓦街
another under goes under Marszalkowska,
一条通向马尔加考斯卡街
third line goes under New Town and Miodowa Street.
一条通向新区和马奥杜瓦街
The Germans keep the courts so busy they have forgotten this entrance.
德国人让法院太忙了 他们忘记了这个出口
You remember our summer walks along the Vistula River?
以还记得那次夏天的散步吗，沿着维斯瓦河的那次？
Every step.
每一步都记得
Shall we?
是吗？
Welcome to Warsaw.
欢迎来到华沙
Thank you, Stefan.
谢谢你，斯忒芬
We will use this way first.
我们先用这条路
- Be careful. - You know me.
- 小心点 - 你知道我的
That is what I mean. Be careful about yourself.
这就是我的意思 自己要小心
Hurry up, hurry up.
快走，快走
Hello.
你好
You remember me? What's your name?
你还记得我吗？ 你叫什么？
The boy who sits beside you every day.
那个每天坐在你旁边的男孩是你哥哥吗？
He died.
他死了
I'm very sorry.
我很遗憾
Can you tell me where you live?
能告诉我你住哪里吗？
All right.
好吧
Come with me.
跟我来
We have hot soup. Just made for you.
我们有热汤 为你做的
Are you going to get her changed in here?
你要在这里改变她的样子吗？
Yes. I think it's a good idea.
是的，我想这是个好主意
- Oh, you are so hungry. - All right.
- 噢，你饿坏了吧 - 好的
We need to do something about her hair.
我们要想想办法怎么搞定她的头发
- Can we braid it? - Please help if you would. All right.
- 我们能给她扎辫子吗？ - 你尽量帮忙吧
- Lets take this skirt off. - Good girl.
- 让我们把裙子脱掉 - 好姑娘
And try a beret.
试试戴个贝雷帽
It will keep you warm.
它能让你暖和一点
Ah, much better. Good girl. You look so beautiful.
啊，好多了，好姑娘 你看起来真漂亮
Ready for a little walk in the courthouse?
准备好在法院大厅里走一段路了吗？
My name is Miriam.
我叫米里亚姆
Come along, sweetie, we must...
快走，亲爱的，我们...
Such a little trouble-maker.
真是个小淘气
You have no idea. Come along, sweetheart.
你不明白，快走，亲爱的
- You want to play with this? - Thank you.
- 你要玩这个吗？ - 谢谢
- Rabbi. - For me?
- 法师 - 给我的？
Such a dashing fashion for a Rabbi.
对法师来说太时髦了
And for you, Miss Nijinska!
这个给你，娜金斯卡小姐！
Oh yes, I remember this book!
哦，是的，我记得这本书
- Come in. Oh, yes. Come in, come in! - Thank you Rabbi.
- 进来，好的，进来，进来！ - 谢谢，法师
So many people without shelter.
这么多无家可归的人
Eva. Hannah, come here.
伊娃，汉娜，到这来
Take this place.
住这里吧
Shall we read a little bit?
我们来看一小段好吗？
Why do I have to be a Jew?
为什么我是犹太人？
You were born into the Jewish faith.
你生在犹太家庭里
What if I want to be something else?
如果我想要成为别的人呢？
I don't like being hated by everybody.
我不想被别人憎恨
Everybody does not hate you.
没人恨你
Yes they do. You know it's true.
不，他们恨我，你知道这是事实
What did we ever do?
我们做了什么？
It's not fair.
这不公平
No, It's not.
是的，是不公平
There are ways to get out of the ghetto, ways that are still safe.
有办法逃出隔离区，而且还是安全的
- I cannot. - Yes, I know.
- 我不能 - 是的，我知道
But I've been thinking about Karolyna.
但是我是在为卡罗玲娜着想
Karolyna?
卡罗玲娜？
We know Polish families who can be trusted, several priests,
我们认识一些值得信任的波兰人
- convents in the countryside. - Stop, Irena!
- 是些住在乡下的神父和修女 - 别说了，伊雷娜！
Let me ask you one thing, tell me from your heart.
我只问你一件事， 你对我说心里话
How is it possible for a mother to give up a child? How?
怎么可能让母亲离开她的孩子？怎么可能？
Now I must ask you something - a terrible thing.
那么现在我必须问你一件事 - 一件可怕的事
No, no don't, please...
别，不要，求你了...
If it happened that the rumors are true
如果那些谣言是真的
and if for Karolyna you had to choose between life and death...
你为卡罗琳娜选择生或者是死
- Please, I cannot face it, I cannot. - You can, Eva - and you must.
- 求你了，我不能面对这些，我不能 - 你可以，伊娃 - 而且你必须选择
Irenka. Do you know what this author says about life?
伊雷娜，你知道这个作者是怎么理解人生的吗？
- Mama, please, I have to go. - Please.
妈妈，我要走了
Take one moment to breathe. Please.
就一小会儿，顺便喘口气
What this writer says is in order to have a happy life,
这个作家说要有一个快乐的人生
you must exercise your own free will.
你就必须按自己的意愿去做
Interesting. Bye-bye.
真有趣，再见
Which is why I would never tell you not to do something or suggest
这就是我为什么从没有告诉你不要做什么事
to you that I might possibly be worried. I would never do such a thing.
或者暗示你我会为了你去做什么而担心 我不会那样做
No matter what happens.
不管发生了什么
Thank you, Mama.
谢谢你，妈妈
Thank you.
谢谢你
- What has happened? - All the Social Service programs
- 发生什么事了？ - 所有的社会服务项目被中止了
From now on only nurses, doctors, workers in the Health Department.
从现在开始，卫生署里只有护士、医生和工人
Today I was told I am officially responsible for any further spread
今天我被告知我将负责防止伤寒的进一步扩散
You know it is impossible, what do they...
你知道，这不可能，为什么他们...
Of course it's impossible. That's their point.
当然不可能 这是他们的问题
If I cannot help myself, how can I help you?
如果我自身难保 又能怎样帮助你呢？
I will need Health Department work passes, four - no, no
我要卫生署的工作证，四张 - 不，不
maybe five nurse's uniforms.
或许五张，还有制服
It that all?
就这些？
Perhaps a larger vehicle.
如果可能的话，要一辆大点的车
We will seek orphans and homeless in the market area and specific families
我们要在市场附近寻找孤儿，还要去那些 愿意把他们的孩子托付给我们的家庭...
One of Doctor Majkowski's drivers has volunteered, Piotr Lipinski.
麦考斯基医生的一个司机自愿来帮我们， 他叫彼得 平斯基
Miss Irena.
伊雷娜小姐
- Hello.
- 你好
Thank you, Piotr. You understand the risk?
谢谢，彼得 你知道风险吗？
Only small problems, but I am not too worried.
只是些小问题， 我不担心
We will take my disinfectant truck.
我们用我的消毒车
- I beg you, keep them together. - I'm sorry, it's not possible.
- 我求你，让他们呆在一起 - 我很抱歉，这不可能
Sister Jolanta, please understand whatever happens they will always
雅尼娜护士长（伊雷娜的化名）， 要知道无论发生什么他们都要彼此拥有
One slip, one word in Yiddish. They could give each other away.
依地语里有句话是说：要学会放弃
How will I ever find them? How will they find each other.
我如何找到他们呢 他们又怎样找到彼此？
The important thing is to survive.
重要的是活下来
Take her. Please go!
抱着他，离开这里，走！
Tell me, what do you want to be when you grow up?
告诉我，你长大了想当什么？
A priest.
神父
Yes, very good, that's perfect!
很好，非常棒！
You can do it.
你会成功的
Papers? Vehicle check.
通行证？车辆检查
What do you have in the truck?
车里装了什么？
- We have a problem. Vehicle check. - All right. Let's go for a walk.
- 我们有麻烦了，车辆检查 - 好吧，我们去散散步
Our Father who art in Heaven,
（基督教主祷词）我们在天上的父，
Hallowed be thy name...
愿人都尊你的名为圣...
Thy kingdom come.
愿你的国降临
Thy will be done on earth, as it is in Heaven.
愿你的旨意行在地上，如同行在天上
Give us this day our daily bread.
我们日用的饮食，今日赐给我们
And forgive us our trespasses,
免我们的债，
as we forgive those who
如同我们免了人的债
Children!
孩子们！
Let's show Miss Irena how we know our bedtime prayers.
让伊雷娜小姐来看看我们的睡前祷告
Now I lay me down to sleep,
现在我躺下入睡
I pray the Lord my soul to keep;
求主保佑我的灵魂
And if I die before I wake,
如果我死在清醒之前
I pray the Lord my soul to take.
求主接纳我的灵魂
First month. Room and board.
这是第一个月的房费和伙食费
Is there anything else I should know?
还有别的事要交代吗？
She had a brother.
她有个哥哥
- This is Adam. - Hello, Adam!
- 这是亚当 - 你好，亚当
- Does he speak Polish? - Perfectly.
- 他会说波兰语吗？ - 说得非常棒
Irena.
伊雷娜
Jacob!
雅各布！
I'm sorry, I didn't mean to frighten you.
我很抱歉， 我不想吓你的
Is Eva all right, Karolyna?
伊娃好吗，还有卡罗琳娜？
Yes, everything's the same.
是的，都还是老样子
Eva has met with community leaders. They want to speak about
伊娃见了社区的领导者
- hiding their children. - Of course.
- 他们想谈谈关于拯救他们孩子的事 - 好的
You had a good instinct,
拯救卡罗琳娜，你很有先见之明
it's risky but there is no other way.
这虽然有风险，但没有其他的办法
And what if my wife and I do not survive the war.
如果我和我妻子没有在这场战争中幸存，
Who will claim our son?
我们的儿子怎么知道谁是他的父母？
I keep a record of every child.
我保存一份每个孩子的记录
And if this record or you are destroyed?
如果记录被毁了或者是你死了呢？
What guarantee can you give our children will survive?
你拿什么保证我们的孩子能够活下来？
I can't guarantee anything, not even escape from the Ghetto.
我不能够保证人和事， 甚至是带他们逃出隔离区也不能保证
Babies pass easily but if they can speak, they must speak Polish,
带孩子们出去容易， 但如果他们会说，就必须说波兰语
know Catholic hymns and prayers.
并且知道基督教赞美诗和祷告词
My children only speak Yiddish.
我的孩子只会说依地语
I understand this is very difficult.
我知道这很困难
They will need to memorize their new Christian names,
他们必须记住他们新的教名
their new home address, the entire history of their new family,
他们新家的地址， 新的家族的整个家族史
harmless gossip about their neighbors - all of it.
以及关于邻居的闲言碎语 - 所有的一切
What you are saying is we must teach our children to lie.
你是说我们要教我们的孩子说谎
To survive, yes.
为了幸免遇难，是的
- What about conversion? - I make it clear I do not wish this.
- 那么改变信仰呢？ - 我说的很清楚了，我也不希望这样
You may not wish it, but on young, impressionable minds,
你也许是不希望那样，但对于孩子来说， 易受影响的思想，
time and education will surely dim any memories of their past.
时间还有教育一定会使他们淡忘自己的过去
In this case, he will grow up a good Christian.
这样，他会成为一个虔诚的基督徒
For mothers and fathers, to give away a child is an unthinkable act.
对于作为父亲和母亲的人来说， 抛弃自己的孩子是难以想象的
This is the truth.
这是事实
The other truth is Hitler calls Jews a cancer on the nation and speaks
但另一个事实是希特勒称犹太人是国家的癌症
openly about the annihilation of every Jew on the continent.
还公开宣称要消灭欧洲大陆所有的犹太人
Outside these walls there are Poles prepared to risk their lives
在隔离区外有一些波兰人正准备 冒着生命危险来救你们的孩子
We Jews - We Jews have survived in the hardest times.
我们犹太人 - 我们犹太人在过去的艰难时代都挺了过来
And now we are faced with another extinction.
现在我们又要面对一个劫难
Perhaps this time we can only be saved by a new generation of Jews.
也许这次只能靠新的一代来拯救犹太民族了
How wise are we to take away the birthright of this new generation?
把生的权利留给新的一代，这是多么明智啊
I recommend we consider this proposal.
我建议我们接受这个提议
Thank you.
谢谢
I am not in favor of sending our children into such a dubious world.
我不赞成把我的孩子送到一个不可靠的地方
Now America is in the war. This news favors our liberation and for this,
现在美国参战了，这个消息预示着我们的解放， 为了这个，我们应该等待
Our dear friend has presented us with the difficult truths of our time.
我们亲爱的朋友给我们带来了艰难的真相
We should thank her for her courage to speak.
我们应该为她勇敢的演讲而感谢她
Quickly.
快点
Jasio go back, there's another bag!
加西欧，你回去， 还有一包没拿！
- No! I will not. - Go get it!
- 不！我不去 - 回去拿来！
Let me go!!!
放开我！！！
No, No!!!
不，不！！！
Sister Jolanta. Walk with me. Please, please.
雅尼娜护士长,请跟我走 请，请
My name is Michal Laski, I know who you are and what you do.
我叫迈克尔 拉斯基， 我知道你是谁，你在干什么
The man you saw just now. He is Untersturmfuhrer Karl Brandt.
你刚才看见的那个人， 他是党卫队三级突击中队长卡尔 勃兰特
He is in charge of Jewish Resettlement. We are told in a few months they will
他负责犹太人的转移
begin to send everyone in the ghetto to work camps in the East.
几个月后他们就要把 隔离区里的每一个人都送到东部的劳工营
- Why do you tell me this? - I have a son - Jasio, 10 years old. His...
- 你为什么告诉我这些？ - 我有一个儿子 - 加西欧，十岁，他的...
His mother died last year. He has no one.
他母亲两年前死了 他没人可以依靠了
- He has you. - He lives with smugglers,
- 他还有你 - 他和那些走私贩生活在一起，
goes under the wall at night, risks his life every day.
在晚上穿过隔离墙走私货物， 为几个小钱卖命
I want to get him out before he's caught and shot.
我想在他被抓住打死之前把他救出去
If from time to time I help you, will you help me?
如果时不时的我帮帮你，你能帮我这个忙吗？
Mr. Laski, I will help your son without conditions.
拉斯基先生，我会帮你儿子的，无条件的
If from time to time you help me, you would be helping many children,
如果时不时的你帮助我，你能救出很多孩子
- including your son. - There's a passage through a brick wall
- 包括你儿子 - 在特沃达街的石墙那里有一个通道
on Twarda Street. On the other side in the abandoned house.
另一边通向一座被废弃的房子
Does your Jasio have red hair like you?
你的加西欧和你一样有一头红发吗？
Yes but thanks to God he now wears a cap.
是的，但是谢天谢地他现在戴了顶帽子
You know about this new German unit now in charge of the Ghetto.
你知道有一队新的德国兵接管了隔离区
Yes, for work camp resettlement.
是的，负责转移行动
Stefan, do not be like this.
斯忒芬，不要这样
You know how many thousands of Jews have disappeared from the Lodz Ghetto.
你知道有多少在罗兹隔离区里的犹太人失踪了
Vanished. And to where? Some place they call Resettlement.
人间蒸发了，他们那里去了？ 这就是他们的转移行动
Doctor Korczak told me to prepare for the worst.
考瑞查克医生让我作最坏的打算
If there is no other way, that is what I must do.
如果没有别的办法， 那我必须那样做
Where is everyone? What has happened?
人呢？ 发生什么事了？
Books, bank accounts, invoices, reciepts they've taken over all of it.
书，银行账户，发票，单据，他们把这些都拿走了
Who?
谁拿走了？
Guten tag.
（德语）中午好
Amen.
阿门
Karolyna, can you tell us why this night is different from all other nights?
卡罗玲娜，你能告诉我们今晚有什么不同吗？
Sweetheart?
亲爱的？
I know why tonight is different.
我知道今晚有什么不同
Tonight is different because once we were slaves and now we are free!
今晚的不同之处在于曾经我们是奴隶，但现在我们自由了！
Jacob!
雅各布！
Papa!
爸爸！
I am not here for Sedar.
我不是来过逾越节的
I have some news you must hear.
我是给你们带消息来的
Eva.
伊娃
The underground received information verified by Polish train machinists,
地下组织收到了一些被波兰铁路机械师证实的消息
some lucky Jews who escaped, even from a few good Germans.
一些幸运的犹太人逃了出来， 甚至是从好心的德国人那里
They all say camps are being built.
他们都说德国人在造集中营，还有劳工营
Concentration camps, work camps. Auschwitz is like this, we know.
奥斯维辛也在造，我们知道的
You remember the thousands of Jews who were deported from Lodz,
你还记得从罗兹遣送来的那些犹太人吗，
the ones who disappeared.
他们失踪了
Last week 300 train cars of clothing returned for sorting.
上星期，有三百节车皮的衣服送回来做分类整理
What else, Jacob?
还有别的吗，雅各布？
We hear rumors they are building another camp. Treblinka.
有谣言说他们还在特雷布林卡建集中营
Only 90 kilometers from Warsaw where there are fake station platforms,
离华沙只有90公里， 那里有伪装的车站月台，
underground bunkers.
地下燃料库
One thing they have not constructed - barracks.
有一样他们没有造 - 营房
No barracks, I do not understand. Why no barracks?
没有营房，我不明白 为什么没有营房？
Mama, they do not...
妈妈，他们不想...
In such a camp, the only purpose is death.
那样的集中营，唯一的作用就是屠杀
We need to find a way to get you out of the Ghetto.
我们要想办法把你们弄出隔离区
Get out, you say! Get out how? Get out to where?
出去，你说，怎么出去？ 去哪里？
Papa,
爸爸
Irena has made an offer for Karolyna.
伊雷娜已经为卡罗玲娜做好了计划
There is a convent in the countryside.
是一个乡下的女修道院
This is not possible. She will be converted! Never!
不行，他要改变信仰，绝对不行！
Chaim!
哈伊姆！
These many months I have said nothing.
这几个月来我什么都没说
Now I will give my opinion.
现在，我说说我的看法
Our dearest Irena has risked her life for us many times.
我们亲爱的朋友伊雷娜已经为我们冒了很多风险
Now, she has made an offer for Karolyna we must accept.
现在，她为卡罗玲娜做好了计划，我们必须接受
- I believe a convent is best. - No, it must not be done.
- 我想女修道院再好不过了 - 不行，不能这样
Chaim Rozenfeld!
哈伊姆 罗兹菲尔德！
You have loved me since I was a little girl in pigtails and after these
你从我还是个扎着辫子的小女孩时就爱上我了
many years you know very well
这么多年来你知道的，我的看法不是建议
Next time, when you come she will be prepared.
下次你来的时候，她会准备好的
Irena, the Underground knows what you're doing.
伊雷娜，地下组织知道你在干什么
They want to help.
他们想提供帮助
There's a man you should speak to, goes by the name Trojan.
你去见一个人，叫特洛伊
24 Zurawia Street.
兹利维亚街24号
For Karolyna, I promise, I will do everything...
我保证，我能为卡罗玲娜做任何事情...
We know that, Irena. We know.
我们知道，伊雷娜，我们知道
I'm Trojan.
我是特洛伊
- And I'm Victor. - Who do you represent?
- 我是维克托 - 你为谁工作？
- Konrad Zegota. - Why me? What do you know?
- 康拉德 泽哥塔 - 为什么找我？你想要什么？
You created an efficient network, saved many children.
你组建了一个非常有效的网络来拯救孩子
So far no one has been betrayed or exposed.
到目前为止没人背叛或暴露
We, with the Underground, have a good deal of money,
我们，还有地下组织，有大量的现金和很多联络点
and contacts. It could be a good arrangement.
这是个很好的基础
- This money, where does it come from? - Polish government in exile in London.
- 这些钱是哪里来的？ - 在伦敦的流亡波兰政府提供的
- To help Jews? - Zegota exists only for that.
- 用来帮助犹太人？ - 泽哥塔的存在就是为了这个
- Who is Konrad Zegota? - He does not exist.
- 谁是康拉德 泽哥塔？ - 他不存在
Which makes him hard to find, especially for Germans
是为了他难以被找到，特别是针对那些从不放弃的德国人
What is your proposal?
你的提议是？
We will help you rescue children. If you agree.
我们将帮助你拯救孩子，如果你同意的话
I agree.
我同意
We'll give you money, Aryan papers, work records.
我们给你提供钱，证明材料，工作证
You'll get them while picking up the linen from the laundry at Bracka street,
你可以在去布莱卡街的洗衣店取衣服时拿到这些
near the Three Crosses Square.
就在三十字广场旁边
This will be our contact point.
那里是我们的一个联络点
- Looks like we're back in business. - Let me count.
- 看起来我们又可以开始工作了 - 让我数数
Look. Identification cards.
看，身份证
Very good work. These will do.
非常好，这些很有用处
- What's going on? - They're deporting adults and children.
- 怎么了？ - 他们在驱逐大人和孩子
- Orphanages? - Yes.
- 孤儿呢？ - 也一样
Stefan.
斯忒芬
You must get out. Do it, for me, for the children.
你必须出去 出去，为了我，为了孩子
You must see and remember and tell the world.
你要见证这些然后告诉世界
- No. - Go. Go on. Quickly.
- 不 - 走，快走，快点
Now. Go, go, quickly!
马上 走，走，快
You know how to do it.
你知道怎么去做的
May God walk with you. Go! Go!
愿上帝与你同在，走！走！
Thanks be to God!
感谢上帝！
They took all the children.
他们带走了所有的孩子
I saw them, I couldn't do anything about it.
我看见了，我什么也做不了
I've heard this news.
我听说了
Who told you?
谁告诉你的？
Your friend.
你的朋友
Let's go son, don't be afraid I'll hide you to keep you warm.
我们走，孩子，不要害怕 我会把你藏好，不会冻着你的
Are you ok?
你还好吧？
- There is a chance today. - Please, one more day, just one.
- 今天有个机会 - 求你了，再给我一天，就一天
Now it is possible, tomorrow is uncertain.
现在还有可能，明天就不确定了
We can't do it now. Please, one more day, just one.
我们现在不能送他走 求你，再给我一天，就一天
Now it's possible. Tomorrow is uncertain.
现在有机会，明天就不一定了
Tomorrow he will be ready,
明天他会准备好的，我保证
You mustn't lock the door.
你们不可以锁上门
Jews who refuse to leave the building will be executed.
拒绝离开的犹太人将被处死
Run downstairs, run.
下楼，快点
No more courthouse entrance.
法院被封了
A big problem.
是个大麻烦
Oh, stop fiddling, You're making me nervous.
噢，别看了， 你搞得我有点紧张
You need to get more rest.
你需要多休息
For Heaven's sake, if I'd had a stroke, I'd be dead.
看在上帝的份上 如果我是中风，我已经死了
I'm telling you, I got up too fast, I fainted. That's all.
我已经告诉你了，我起来的太快了， 就晕倒了，就这些
You are in bad condition, I'm not joking.
你的状况不好， 我不是开玩笑
You are a very brave young woman.
你是个勇敢的女人
Stefan?
斯忒芬？
There's room for two.
这里容得下两个人
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
A little carpentry.
一些木工活
What do you think?
你觉得呢？
I feel a little bit confined. I think I need to get out.
我感到有点挤， 我想出去了
It's, it's not opening. It's stuck.
打不开，它卡住了
It, it, hmm...
它，它，呃...
Can you please try? Please.
你能试着打开吗？
- It's stuck from the outside. - No. Please, open it. Please.
- 它从外面被卡住了 - 不，打开它
OK. All right, I need to, we need to get out of here.
好的，我要，我们应该出去
We must call your mother.
我们要提醒一下你妈妈
Mama?
妈妈？
Irenka?
伊雷卡？
Jasio?
加西欧？
Do you remember?
你还记得我吗？
I can't leave them. I will not.
我不能离开他们，我不能
You, you have done a good thing, Jasio, a very important thing
你已经做得很好了，加西欧
and it may be hard to understand but the future will
重要的是未来比现在更需要你的同情心， 你可能不太明白这些
Which is why tomorrow you must save yourself.
这就是为什么明天你必须拯救你自己
You know the coal room? Where the Rabbis study?
你知道煤房在哪里吗？ 就是法师们学习的地方
Two o'clock tomorrow my friend will meet you there.
明天两点钟我朋友会在那里等你
She wears bright red lipstick.
她涂着鲜红色的口红
Be strong, say your good byes.
坚强点，向他们道别
I will never see you again.
我再也见不到你了
I will never see any of you again, any of you.
我再也见不到你们了，你们所有人
Yes, you will, I promise.
是的，我想是的
No, you can't promise. Nobody can promise anything any more!
不，没人能保证未来会发生什么！
Darling. Darling, darling,
亲爱的！
I love you with all my heart.
我全心全意的爱你
My love for you is so big and strong it will never go away.
我对你的爱永远不会消失
It will always be with you.
它将永远伴随你
Whenever you think of me, I will be there, right over your shoulder.
什么时候你想起我，我就在你身边
Forever and ever.
永远
- Your name? - Aniela Procowna.
- 你的名字？ - 安吉拉 波洛康纳
- And where are you from? - Krakow, Poland.
- 你来自哪里？ - 波兰 克拉科夫
But when I grow up I want to live in Bavaria.
但是当我长大了我想住在巴伐利亚
My uncle says Germany is much more beautiful...
我叔叔说德国要美丽多了...
- Your name? - Aniela Procowna.
- 你的名字？ - 安吉拉 波洛康纳
- And where are you from? - Krakow, Poland.
- 你来自哪里？ - 波兰 克拉科夫
But when I grow up I want to live in Bavaria. My uncle...
但是当我长大了我想住在巴伐利亚，我叔叔...
Quick, quick in!
快，快！
Out, out. Get out of here. Out, get out! Out. Out!
出来，从里面出来，出来！
I will not!
不要！
Jasio?
加西欧？
Mr. Laski!
拉斯基先生！
Out, out!
下来，下来！
You - come with me!
你 - 跟我来！
And you, come! Move.
还有你，过来，快点！
Get away from here - but slowly.
从这里走出去 - 慢慢的
- I saw Jasio. He will get out. - Thank you.
- 我见过加西欧了，他会出去的 - 谢谢
Maria.
玛丽亚
Jasio?
加西欧呢？
I know.
我知道了
Come. Come.
来，来
Jasio!
加西欧！
Jasio! No!
加西欧！不！
Let me through.
让我过去
Jasio!
加西欧！
Papa, papa.
爸爸，爸爸
- I tried to get out but they... - It's all right, it's all right.
- 我试着逃出去但是他们... - 没关系，没关系
All that matters is that we are together.
最重要的是我们在一起了
Hold onto to me so we don't get separated.
抓住我，别挤散了
Faster, faster.
快点，快点
Hold on to me, hold on to me. - Simon!
抓住我，抓住我 - 西蒙！
There has been a mistake! No! He's my son!
一定是搞错了！ 不！他是我儿子！
My family is protected!
我的家人是受保护的！
All Jews inside!
所有的犹太人进去！
Everyone inside!
所有人进去！
Papa!
爸爸！
Jasio!
加西欧！
Papa! Papa!
爸爸！爸爸！
Jasio, I understand now why you lived in the street.
加西欧，现在我明白了你为什么住在街上
It was God's way to make you strong so you can survive.
这是上帝的方法，让你强壮，这样你才能活下来
Here, give him my sweater.
给，把我的毛衣给他
I cannot do it. I'm afraid, Papa. Please, I can't.
我做不到，我害怕，爸爸 求你，我做不到
- Yes, you can. Yes, you can. - No. I can't. Please. I'm afraid.
- 你能行的，你能行的， - 我做不到，我害怕
Jasio, listen to me.
加西欧，听着
Land on your elbows, keep your head down.
手臂着地，低下头
- Come with me. - Keep your head down and stay
- 跟我一起下去 - 低下头直到火车开过去
I love you, Papa.
我爱你，爸爸
Then you must run as fast as you can into the trees.
然后你必须以最快速度跑到树林里去
I love you, Papa. Please! Come with me. I don't want to please!
我爱你，爸爸，求你！跟我一起走
Shh. Shh! Be quiet! You must be brave.
嘘，嘘！安静点！拿出你的勇气来
I can't! Papa! I can't. Please come with me. Please.
我做不到！爸爸！我做不到 跟我一起走，求你
One.
一
- No! Please! - One, two.
- 不！求你了！ - 一，二
Papa!
爸爸！
Three!
三！
...my God.
...天哪
Look at that.
来看看这个
Thank you.
谢谢
My darling.
好孩子
Children! Children, shh.
孩子们！孩子们，嘘
Children, this is Anielka. She will be joining us.
孩子们，这是安吉拉 她将加入我们的行列
Please don't leave me, please.
别离开我，别
This war will end and you will survive to be a mother and tell your story.
战争会结束的，你会幸存下来，为人母， 给孩子们讲你的经历
And one day, if we are both very clever,
如果我们都够聪明，
I will find you. I promise.
有一天我会找到你的 我保证
Now there is something you must promise me.
现在你必须对我保证一件事
You must promise that you will always remember that
你保证你要永远记住你是著名的娜金斯卡小姐，芭蕾舞团之首席女演员
I love you.
我爱你
Me too.
我也是
Shouldn't you have taught me this as a child?
我小时候你没教我吗？
- Over and under. - It's beautiful.
- 绕过去，再往下 - 这很漂亮
- You are so mean. - It is a mess do it again.
- 你太迟钝了 - 再织就弄乱了
- He's telling the truth. - It's hideous.
- 他说的没错 - 这很难看
This is never going to be...
这个怎么弄都不会...
I give up.
我放弃
Gestapo.
盖世太保
I will do it.
让我来
Irena Sendler?
伊雷娜 森德勒？
I am.
是的
- Look in the bathroom and kitchen.
- 去浴室和厨房看看
Do you have Jews here?
你们这里藏有犹太人吗？
Of course not. It's against the law.
当然没有，那是违法的
We'll find out.
我们会找出来的
You will come with us.
你跟我们走
Let me get a few things.
让我拿点东西
There's no need.
没这个必要了
Irena Sendler, good afternoon.
伊雷娜 森德勒，下午好
I work for Department of Social Services.
我为社会服务部工作
I know. I know.
我知道，我知道
Your father was a doctor, worked with Jews.
你父亲是医生，为犹太人看病
- He worked with anyone who was sick. - Yes. Until the Jews gave him Typhus.
- 他为任何生病的人看病 - 是的，直到犹太人传染给他伤寒
Who is Konrad Zegota?
谁是康拉德 泽哥塔？
Who?
谁？
I don't know.
我不知道
Who is Konrad Zegota?
谁是康拉德 泽哥塔？
You have been denounced by many people.
你被很多人告发了
For example, the little shop where you pick up
比如，布莱卡街三十字广场边洗衣店的小伙计的
your laundry on Bracka Street near Three Crosses Square.
就是你拿衣服的那个店
We know you are not so involved with these criminals.
我们知道你和那些家伙的关系不是很密切
And if you tell us where to find this man you will not be executed.
如果你能告诉我们这个人在那里，我们就不处决你
Sendler, out!
森德勒，出来
What does it mean?
这是什么意思？
Sendler. Dentist.
森德勒，你的牙医来了
ZEGOTA WILL HELP. You're wasting your time and mine.
纸条：泽哥塔会救你出去的 德国兵：你在浪费你的时间，还有我的
I'm ordered to place a dressing, I place a dressing.
有人让我带件裙子进来，我就带来了
For what? She will be dead in the morning.
还有什么用？她明早就要死了
I do what I'm told, that's all.
别人让我做什么，我就做什么，就是这样
Stefania?
斯特凡尼亚？
You're alive!
你还活着！
I swear, I told them nothing. I was quiet as a mouse.
我发誓，我什么也没说 我安静得像只老鼠一样
- You know I would never betray you. - As a good soldier.
- 你知道我是不会出卖你的 - 就像一个出色的士兵一样
- Yes. - A good soldier.
- 是的 - 一个出色的士兵
You have done very well.
你已经做得很好了
Everyone out! Out!
所有人出来！下车！
Not you!
你过来！
No! No, wait. Wait!
不！不！等等！等等！
Aim!
瞄准！
Fire!
开火！
Get away from here! Go! Go!
离开这里！快走！快走！
Go!
走啊！
But, I, I don't have my identification card!
但是，我，我没有身份证！
Stupid woman! You are dead! With them. Go! Run away! Get out!
笨蛋！你死了！和他们一起， 走，快跑！快跑啊！
Irena!
伊雷娜！
Viktor.
维克托
They'll find out. And they'll look for you.
他们会查出来的， 然后他们会到处找你
I'll be safe.
我会没事的
Your mother is right, your feet need a specialist.
你妈妈是对的， 你的脚要让个专家来看看
I know it's hard but please try not to walk too much.
我知道这要求有点过分，但要你尽量少走动
Promise me...
向我保证...
you won't come to my funeral.
别来参加我的葬礼
- Mama, don't say such things. - Promise me.
- 妈妈，别说这些 - 向我保证
Irenka.
伊雷卡
Can I tell you something.
我想告诉你
I'm...
我...
proud...
为你...
of you.
自豪
Very proud
非常自豪
So many I could not save.
还有那么多孩子我救不了
You've done a good and decent thing.
你已经做得很好了
In this world that's not so bad.
在这种世道下已经很不错了
It's time.
时间到了
We must be in the mountains before dark.
我们必须在天黑之前赶到山里
Mama.
妈妈
Don't worry,
别担心我
I'll be fine.
我感觉很好
Go.
走吧
Wait, Irena.
等等，伊雷娜
Trojan.
特洛伊
Thank you so much for all you've done.
谢谢你所做的一切
No. Thank you.
不，谢谢你们
There's something Konrad Zegota must have.
有一些东西必须交给康拉德 泽哥塔
They're all here.
他们都在这里
Every child.
每个孩子
Where we hid them.
我把他们藏在哪里
When all this is over,
当这一切都结束了，
they must be returned to whatever remains of their families.
他们一定要回到自己的家里，不管那个家还剩下多少人
I will do it. I promise.
我会去做的，我保证
Thank you.
谢谢
From now on you are Klara Dabrowska.
从现在起，你就是克拉拉 东布罗夫斯卡了
Once upon a time, there was a little girl
从前，有一个小女孩
I am so fond of stories that begin that way.
我太喜欢这样的故事开头了
I have kielbasa, bread...
我这里有 波兰熏肠，面包...
- You like? - Yes, I do.
- 你喜欢吗？ - 是的，我喜欢
Good!
啊！
- First, you must come meet my pigs. - Really Piotr, that's not necessary.
- 但是，首先，你要来看看我的猪 - 真的吗，彼得，没这个必要了
One thing I can say about town folk, they make terrible farmers.
我要说关于城里人的是，他们的农活做得太差了
Please, let me down.
让我下来
Oh, thank God.
噢，感谢上帝
- Are you all right? - Now, yes
- 你好吗？ - 现在，很好
We must fight for what is good.
我们必须为了美好的东西而战斗
Good must prevail.
我们一定会胜利的
It must prevail and I believe in this.
我坚信我们会胜利的
As long as I'm alive...
只要我还活着...
as long as I have strength...
只要我还有力气...
I will say good is best.
我会说那些东西是最美好的
Love,
爱
tolerance
宽容
and humility
还有谦卑
- -that's it.
- 就是这些